<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
    which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="std" docName="draft-rigatoni-lsr-isis-fragment-timestamping-00" ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" tocDepth="3" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3">

    <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

    <front>

        <title>Optional IS-IS Fragment Timestamping</title>

        <author initials='T.' surname='Przygienda' fullname='Tony Przygienda'>
            <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
            <address>
                <email>prz@juniper.net</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <author initials='C.' surname='Barth' fullname='Colby Barth'>
            <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
            <address>
                <email>cbarth@juniper.net</email>
            </address>
        </author>




        <date/>

        <abstract>

        <t>


            Many applications in today’s networks rely on reliable and timely flooding of link-state information,
            such as, but not limited to Traffic Engineered networks.  If such link-state information is delayed
            it can be difficult for those applications to adequately fulfill their intended functionality.
            This document describes extensions
            to ISIS allowing carrying of fragment origination time.  The origination time can be used to aid
            troubleshooting and/or by the applications themselves to improve their behavior.

            </t>


        </abstract>

    </front>

    <middle>

            <section title="Introduction" anchor="intro">
                <t>
  Many applications in today’s networks rely on reliable and timely flooding of link-state information, such as,
  but not limited to Traffic Engineered networks and advanced telemetry solutions.  If such information is delayed during
  flooding it can be difficult for those
  applications to adequately fulfill their intended purpose.  This document describes extensions to ISIS allowing it
  to carry the origination time on each fragment.
  The origination time can be used to aid troubleshooting of large domains and/or by the applications themselves
  to improve their behavior.
  </t>
  <t>
            As an example, in case of Traffic Engineered Networks synchronization of the Traffic Engineering Database (TED) enables
            the compute nodes to adapt to changes in the network state and/or react to network events in a timely manner.
            Relying on a synchronized TED while the flooding information is delayed can easily lead
             to service degradation due to substandard re-optimization of network load.
              In case fragments carry their origination time proposed in this document meant for consumption by the
              compute nodes or by an operator of a Traffic Engineered Network and allow to measure any delays in TED synchronization.
              The awareness of delays incurred in the distribution of information can be incorporated further into algorithms
              and network tooling to improve the responsiveness and quality of decisions taken.
              </t>

              <t>
            A requirement for the correct interpretation of the additions proposed in this document is an
            infrastructure synchronizing time across devices involved so the timestamps at the various points
            of interest become comparable.
            This could be accomplished by utilizing Precision Time Protocol (PTP) IEEE Std. 1588 <xref target="IEEEstd1588"/>
            or 802.1AS <xref target="IEEEstd8021AS"/> designed for bridged LANs and the achieved precision is carried
                  in the timestamp.

                </t>
            </section>

            <section title="Timestamp TLV" anchor="tlvs">
                <t>This section defines a new, optional TLV that can be present in any fragment. In case of multiple
                copies only the first occurrence MUST be used. The semantics of the TLV is the point in time the
                fragment with the current sequence number has been generated. Its absence signifies that such
                information is not available. </t>
                <t>
                    For practical purposes, although desirable, timestamping the moment a fragment is flooded
                    would be preferable but beside practical implementation problems this could generate on different
                    interfaces the same fragment with different content which breaks one of the fundamental
                    tenants of link-state protocols. However, an implementation is free to choose to use, e.g. the moment
                    the fragment is queued for flooding first time rather than the time the version is generated.
                </t>
                <t>To save space the timestamp is following semantically <xref target="IEEEstd1588"/> with the exception of
                    shorter seconds field including a wrap-around for the epoch and
                    carrying only 2^-4 of second as maximum resolution of the timestamp since this is considered
                    sufficient for link-state purposes. The specification follows guidelines of <xref target="RFC8877"/>.
                </t>


                <figure align="left">
                    <artwork align="left" type="ascii-art"><![CDATA[
   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |     Type      |     Length    |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |                         Seconds                               |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  | Frac  | Prec  |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

  ]]></artwork>
                </figure>

                <ul>
                    <li>Type: TBD1</li>

                    <li>Length: ...</li>

                    <li>Seconds: 4 bytes of number of seconds since the PTP epoch and following its semantics at
                        shortened length. Any value
                    smaller than 0x5000_0000 (roughly AD 2012) MUST be considered as 2^32 + field value (i.e. a
                        number larger than 2^32).
                    The resulting wraparound will occur in the year 2078.</li>
                    <li>Fraction: 4-bits of fraction of the second in units of 2^-4 which is  equivalent
                        to 1/16 of a second or 60 msec. </li>
                    <li>Precision: 4 bits indicating the maximum possible slip (either in future or past)
                        of the clock used to generate the
                        timestamp (depending on the synchronization
                    protocol) as 2^-Precision where at minimum of the range 0 signifies 1 second precision (minimum required)
                        and at maximum of the range 16
                    indicates a precision of 60 msecs or better. For practical purposes this can be as well the
                    minimum precision of the synchronization protocol, e.g. stratum deviation.</li>
                </ul>

            </section>



    </middle>

    <back>

        <references title="Normative References">


            <!--
            <reference anchor="ISO10589">
                <front>
                    <title>Intermediate system to Intermediate system intra-domain
                        routeing information exchange protocol for use in conjunction with
                        the protocol for providing the connectionless-mode Network Service
                        (ISO 8473)
                    </title>

                    <author>
                        <organization abbrev="ISO">International Organization for Standardization</organization>
                    </author>

                    <date month="Nov" year="2002"/>
                </front>

                <seriesInfo name="ISO/IEC" value="10589:2002, Second Edition"/>
            </reference>
            -->

            <reference anchor="IEEEstd1588" target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/4579760/">
                <front>
                    <title>IEEE Standard for a Precision Clock Synchronization Protocol for
                        Networked Measurement and Control Systems</title>
                    <seriesInfo name="IEEE" value="Standard 1588"/>
                    <author>
                        <organization>IEEE</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date/>
                </front>
            </reference>

 <reference anchor="IEEEstd8021AS" target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/5741898/">
        <front>
            <title>IEEE Standard for Local and Metropolitan Area Networks - Timing
                and Synchronization for Time-Sensitive Applications in Bridged Local
                Area Networks</title>
            <seriesInfo name="IEEE" value="Standard 802.1AS"/>
            <author>
                <organization>IEEE</organization>
            </author>
            <date/>
        </front>
    </reference>

        </references> <!-- end of normative references -->

        <references title="Informative References">
            <xi:include href='https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml'/>
            <xi:include href='https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8877.xml'/>

        </references> <!-- end of informative references -->

    </back>

</rfc>
